Guide to the UE International Department Records, 1945-2003 UE.11
ULS Archives & Special Collections
UE International Department Records
1945-2003
ULS Archives & Special Collections
United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America
UE.11
8.75 Linear Feet (7 boxes)
The United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America (UE) developed its international department as a way for the union to address concerns associated with globalization. This record group contains correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings regarding the UE and United States' involvement in international labor relations.
History
The United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America (UE) created its international department as a way for the union to address concerns associated with globalization. Beginning in 1945, the World Federation of Trade Unions was developed as the first real attempt at international labor solidarity allowing the Congress of Industrial Organizations in the United States, of which the UE was a part, to connect with other unions in the Soviet Union, Europe, Africa, Asia, and Latin America. As the Cold War set in, this group was split along ideological lines. Then in 1992, the UE developed the Strategic Organizing Alliance with Mexico's Frente Autentico del Trabajo, or Authentic Labor Front (FAT), in the pursuit of promoting international solidarity. Together, these organizations collaborate in educational and organizational efforts. In 1998 the UE joined the International Federation of Chemical, Energy and Mine and General Workers' Unions (ICEM) which is a global secretariat of labor unions. Since then, the UE has formed alliances with other labor unions around the world.
Scope and Content Notes
This record group contains correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings regarding the UE and United States' involvement in international labor relations. Included is information on the World Federation of Trade Unions, as well international labor law and international solidarity work from the 1960s to the 1980s. Other files include records of a 1998 North American Free Trade Agreement National Administrative Office case between Echlin Inc. and several unions in Mexico, Canada, and the United States. Echlin was alleged to have hired 170 people to hold workers at a plant near Mexico City hostage to prevent them from joining a real labor union. Records regarding a UE trip to the Soviet Union in 1977 and issues of Mexican Labor News are also present.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged by topic.
Access Restrictions
Records of the United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America are closed for a period of twenty-five years after their creation.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the United Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers of America on 1986, 1994, 1997, 2003, and 2004.
Previous Citation
UE International Department Records, 1945-2003, UE.11, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Labor unions and international relations; Labor unions -- Canada; Labor unions -- Mexico; Labor unions -- United States -- History; International labor activities; Labor; Electric industry workers -- Labor unions -- United States -- History; Commission for Labor Cooperation. Canadian National Administrative Office; Echlin Inc; Frente Auténtico del Trabajo (Mexico); NAFTA Secretariat; World Federation of Trade Unions
- World Federation of Trade Unions, 1945-1962 (Box 1)
- World Federation of Trade Unions, 1963-1966 (Box 2)
- Latin American Labor, 1957-1969 (Box 2)
- Cross Boarder Mural Campaign, 1990s (Box 3)
- Mexican Labor News and Analysis, 1996-1999 (Box 3)
- Mexican Labor News and Analysis, 2000-2003 (Box 4)
- Foreign Correspondence and Research (Box 4)
- National Administrative Office v. Echlin, 1998 (Box 5-6)
- Canadian National Administrative Office Pamphlets, 1998 (Box 7)
- UE Trip to the Soviet Union, 1977 (Box 7)